<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>journey on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/categories/journey/</link>
    <description>Recent content in journey on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/categories/journey/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Yearly goals: 2022 targets</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/01/20/goals-2022-targets/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/01/20/goals-2022-targets/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;This is the second part in a series of posts about setting and tracking my yearly goals when it comes to Machine Learning &amp;amp; Data Science (ML &amp;amp; DS) as well as Sports &amp;amp; Exercise. In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/01/13/goals-2021-results/&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about my past goals for 2021 and the lessons learned from those. This post will focus on my goals and expectations for 2022, and how last year’s experiences shaped and informed them. This might be more fun to read if you’ve seen the &lt;del&gt;comedy show&lt;/del&gt; documentary Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;stretch-to-avoid-injuries&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stretch to avoid injuries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the summary tweet with my stretch goals from the 1st of January:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;My 2022 stretch goals:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Spend 400 h learning ML/DS&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Join 2 NLP + 2 Image competitions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kaggle?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@kaggle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Team up in 3 competitions&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Win 2 Kaggle comp medals&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Write 50 blog posts&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Run a sub-4h marathon&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Do 1 muscle up&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Sleep at least 8 h/night with a std dev &amp;lt;= 0.5 h&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Martin Henze (Heads or Tails) (@heads0rtai1s) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/heads0rtai1s/status/1477360618432778242?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;January 1, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of those being &lt;em&gt;stretch&lt;/em&gt; goals is that I’m not expecting to reach all of them. And that would be fine. Because the important aspect is the &lt;strong&gt;journey towards those goals&lt;/strong&gt;, and the skills and experiences that I hope this journey will give me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals themselves are still important, and I will do my best in reaching them. Some will go better than others. Trying to become better at something can be a vague target, and concrete goals can be very useful in providing a metric to measure progress and success. Similar to ML, finding a good metric can make a big difference. And of course also similar to ML any metric can be gamed; but you would only be fooling yourself. Thus, when striving for those goals it is essential to remember the purpose behind them, and the vision you had when setting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/mXuPwP0kxQqvu0M168/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Maybe not that kind of vision&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;spend-400-h-learning-mlds&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Spend 400 h learning ML/DS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in the previous post, hours themselves don’t create mastery. Spending your time effectively is more important that spending lots of it with vague intentions. My aspiration here is to grow my ML/DS skills in specific directions. I realised that I’m still lacking the kind of solid understanding of many ML concepts that would allow me to use them as confidently and creatively as I would like to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me try to illustrate what I mean. When I encounter a certain data problem - be it on Kaggle, at work, or anywhere - then in my head I construct ideas for ways to process the data to make it easier to solve the problem. For instance, for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/c/titanic&#34;&gt;Kaggle Titanic&lt;/a&gt; challenge I would try to come up with feature engineering steps to figure out whether someone was travelling alone or in groups, and what kind of groups those could be (family? friends?). That’s the creative part. Translating these ideas into code is where the skill comes in. For traditional (tabular) ML I’m reasonably good at this translation, but when it comes to Deep Learning (DL) my process is still slow and inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the tabular ML and feature engineering flow, I also know what to aim for in my skill development through the analogy to data visualisation. I’m a big fan of dataviz, and it arguably contributed a lot to my early successes in the Kaggle community. When it comes to a visualisation problem, I’m able to envision the data in my head and then find the right (ggplot2) tools to realise my imagination through code. Ideas flow almost unimpeded through the power of dataviz skills and tools. From there, my limitations (which are still plenty) mostly arise from a lack in creativity rather than from my coding skills. And this is where I want to be with ML/DL. Maybe not this year; but I want to get much closer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;join-2-nlp-2-image-competitions-on-kaggle&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Join 2 NLP + 2 Image competitions on Kaggle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to make my ML goals even more concrete is through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/competitions&#34;&gt;Kaggle competitions&lt;/a&gt;. Challenges throughout the year are manifold and diverse. They typically attract a few thousand people, hundreds among whom are sharing their ideas or code. I can’t think of a better way of learning than to immerse yourself into such a competition for (typically) 3 months and soak up the skills and problem solving ingenuity that others display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I want to improve my skills in Image problems (aka Computer Vision) and Natural Language Processing (NLP). Both of those are solidly in the domain of DL these days. Image-based challenges are usually plentiful throughout the year. NLP competitions can be less frequent, but it should hopefully still be possible to encounter 2 interesting ones in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to Image data, I’m reasonably happy with my progress in 2021. I started learning about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fast.ai&#34;&gt;FastAI&lt;/a&gt; and using it more confidently in building my own competition pipeline and tinkering with custom dataloaders in some competitions. I also started to look into the underlying basic functionality in &lt;a href=&#34;https://pytorch.org&#34;&gt;Pytorch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://torch.mlverse.org&#34;&gt;torch for R&lt;/a&gt; (FastAI is a high-level wrapper for Pytorch). While the way that torch works is pretty intuitive, I need to spend more time with the code itself to become more confident in using it creatively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For NLP, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co&#34;&gt;huggingface libraries&lt;/a&gt; have fast become the gold standard, and the ecosystem is growing and evolving rapidly. I enjoyed taking the first &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/course/chapter1/1&#34;&gt;huggingface course&lt;/a&gt; last year, and I plan to continue with those courses to learn more. There are a few libraries that bring the huggingface tools into the FastAI ecosystem; which is an ideal combination for me at this stage. I plan to focus on those, besides the general huggingface framework, and will hopefully blog about it every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/LpR8z8GqoyktA3141E/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;I promise I&amp;#39;ll try my best to blog about it.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;team-up-in-3-competitions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Team up in 3 competitions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thoroughly enjoyed my teaming up experiences in 2021 and plan to continue this approach in 2022. There is a lot that you can learn from your team mate(s) on Kaggle, since many people come from such different professional and technical backgrounds. The goal of 3 competitions seems relatively low compared to the rest of the goals, but I’m aiming for gradual progress here. Last year it was 2 competitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the right balance in a team can be a challenge, as is the way that progress is planned and implemented. Communication is really crucial here; as in so many areas of life. This applies not necessarily to the goal of doing well in a Kaggle competition, but to getting the most out of the learning experiences that are enabled by the process of collaboration. In all of those aspects I consider myself fortunate in having teamed up with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/YassineAlouini&#34;&gt;Yassine&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m looking forward to our future collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/jsI8nBXJl6s7r7iuJ5/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Tres competiciones&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;win-2-kaggle-comp-medals&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Win 2 Kaggle comp medals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021, I purposefully didn’t set a goal of a certain performance in a Kaggle competition. I just wanted to grow my (DL) skills by spending more time on Kaggle problems. Now, I feel like I’m at a stage where I can expect to develop those skills to the extend where my progress translates to better finishes on competition leaderboards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a fan of the Kaggle medal system, and of the gamification aspect in general. I consider it an incarnation of the idea of concrete metrics replacing otherwise vague goals that I wrote about at the beginning of this post. But here there can be an even greater incentive to game the system and take the medals as a goal in themselves, rather than a reflection of your skills. Sometimes, it might be possible to win a (bronze) medal by forking a public notebook or blindly ensembling other people’s solutions without understanding them (and getting lucky in the shake-up). That’s not what I want. Those medals don’t really count for anything, since they are disconnected from your actual abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to write my own code and understand (ideally) every line of it. Inspired by other people’s ideas, yes; but incorporating those inspirations purposefully and in an informed way into my own pipelines. Plan my experiments intelligently and choose the best progress based on the results of those experiments. Those medals will mean something. Most importantly, they will mean something to me. Setting this goal and putting it out there will create a bit more pressure to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/QrcujnCu5qWVyea2Xc/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Maybe it was a bit too much pressure.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;write-50-blog-posts&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Write 50 blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogging was an aspect of my journey that suffered in 2021. Of the 12 posts that I had planned, I wrote only 2. But instead of lowering the bar more, I decided to raise it to 50 instead. This might not make a lot of intuitive sense, since a target of 50 looks way more intimidating than a mere dozen. However, I realised that it wasn’t really the number of posts that stopped me from writing. It was the process of writing a single posts, which I saw as a significant endeavour that needed preparation and research and comprehensive content to be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can be a bit of a perfectionist, which sometimes stops me from making public something that I had written but wasn’t happy with. And I would hate to turn into the kind of spammer who just churns out cookie-cutter posts in the search for engagement and followers. You know the ones. Although I don’t expect a large audience for those posts, I want to write something of value for those who stumble across my blog. There’s enough noise on the internet already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the crux: writing valuable content doesn’t have to mean writing long and/or polished content. Short snippets of concise code or brief reflections on recent learnings can have as much value as posts that have been months in the making. I simply need to get out of my comfort zone and write more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One benefit of writing is analogous to the idea that teaching a concept to someone is a great way of learning about this concept. If you can’t explain it, then do you really understand it? And if you can’t write about it clearly and concisely, then chances are you don’t actually understand it either. But understanding something is not necessarily a binary thing, and sharing even small progress in learning can be useful to people in similar situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after writing only 2 posts in 2021 (albeit more technical posts), this will be already the second post of 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;run-a-sub-4h-marathon&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Run a sub-4h marathon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first ever marathon in 2021 (not a race, just the distance) clocked in at 4 hours 25 minutes. Not too bad; now let’s see whether we can get under 4 hours. Shaving off 25 minutes of 42km might not look much at the outset, but it’s about 35s per km, which here is the difference between a 5:45 pace (4h-goal) and a 6:20 pace (last year), which is pretty noticeable. (Being European, I measure my pace in min/km.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My pace for shorter runs is significantly faster than that; and I’ve run a personal best 1h 40min half-marathon (i.e. 4:45 pace). However, a marathon becomes very different after the 2h mark, and most certainly during the final 10km. I will probably still need to take short stretches of walking with water and energy gels, which need to be factored into the overall running pace. I feel like being at 5:00 pace for the first half and then aiming for 5:30 - 6:30 pace for the remainder sounds realistic. In contrast, last year I dropped to 7:30 pace for the last 12km, albeit having done quite well until km 25. My plan is to work more on the stages between km 20 and 30 with long training runs of 2h to 3h durations during most weekends. Should be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/cnipK4uGHhudr6tels/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;We might have different definitions of &amp;#39;fun&amp;#39;.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;do-1-muscle-up&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Do 1 muscle up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a repetition of the 2021 goal, since I didn’t accomplish anything in that direction. For 2022, I will have to build a better plan to make at least some progress. I’m pretty sure that a muscle up is mostly a question of technique, given a certain level of strength. None of that silly cross-fit-style swingy stuff though; I’m talking about proper technique. There are different stages of the muscle up movement, and I hope to be able to train some of those in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to build out the strength first (and my pull up continuity in 2021 wasn’t too bad), this year I will invest more time to research the technique and put together a plan to get me progressively closer to my goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sleep-at-least-8-hnight-with-a-std-dev-0.5-h&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sleep at least 8 h/night with a std dev &amp;lt;= 0.5 h&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last goal might sound weirdly specific, but it’s all about continuity. As a student, then PhD student, then astronomer (of all things!) it’s easy to slip into weird sleeping habits. Even if you don’t actually have to spend your nights at a telescope. Working at a startup might sound like one of those “out of the frying pan and into the fire” type situations when it comes to being sleep deprived, but I’m happy to tell you that there are startups who recognise the value of a healthy work-life balance. Since more and more research is highlighting the importance of a good night’s sleep, I identified this goal as foundational for all the other goals in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s honestly also something that you should listen to your body for. From time to time it might be necessary to work late to meet a deadline, but the thought that your brain won’t be impacted by only 4h of shut-eye is pretty untenable. You pay for burning the midnight oil with reduced cognitive spark over the following days, so your average productivity still goes down even though you worked all those extra hours. And you might be able to get away with it for a while in your 20s, since that’s pretty much the kind of bad decisions that your 20s are for, but it’s still gonna catch up with you eventually. Anyway, no lecturing intended here. Sleep is super important, and I suggest to use it smartly to get where you want to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about that goal? Well, last year I managed to exceed my planned average of 8h / night. But you can famously drown in a river that’s only 30cm deep on average. Variance matters, and there was too much of that in my sleep patterns. Once more, I was looking for a concrete goal to improve my habits. A standard deviation of less than 30 mins means that in 67% of nights I would be less than +/- 15 min away from my average goal. That sounds broadly doable. Last year’s standard deviation was 1h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not suggesting to run around with a stop watch either, or try to plan your day down to the minute. That’s a recipe for a neurotic type of disaster worthy of a silly and slightly problematic 80s comedy. My approach is to pay a bit more attention to guide my habits towards being more sustainable and then let routine take over. You won’t always able to stick to those habits every single day, but if you’re generally maintaining them that’s already a big improvement. So don’t sleep on sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/Qw4X3FJbFEXeglZ7s6A/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Especially when travelling long distances.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you know some of my plans for 2022. I’d be happy to read about yours, in whichever shape or form you’d like to share them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have noticed a pattern in most of my goals, and that is something I will write about more in detail in a future post: my overarching aim is for my 2022 self to be better than my 2021 self. Comparing yourself to other people can be a futile and demoralising exercise, especially if you, like me, tend to look to the most high-achieving people in your field or community for inspiration. Even more so in this age of social media highlight reels. In contrast, I believe that comparing yourself to a previous baseline of yourself can be a great way to learn from past mistakes and experiences. Look at what worked, slightly tweak those things that didn’t work to see if that improves the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the basis for ML experiments, which comes from the basis of any science experiments, which comes from the scientific method, which comes from an evidence-based approach to trying to understand this often perplexing world in which we find ourselves. Reflecting on your choices and their consequences is a valuable tool in any context. Or as Socrates used to say: “The unexamined life is not worth living”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third and final part of this goals series I will write about measuring my goals and (finally!) bring in some code and visualisations. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/mXuPwxly5V2xL1uAow/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Go and be awesome!&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yearly goals: 2021 experiences</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/01/13/goals-2021-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/01/13/goals-2021-results/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of last year, I got the motivation from other people’s Twitter posts to set and track my own goals for what would surely be the year we would emerge from the shadows of the pandemic. With an ever so slightly more jaded outlook to life, I’m doing the same this year. On a global level, many societies didn’t seem to have learned an aweful lot from the Covid years of 2020 and 2021. From a personal perspective, I hope that the experience of setting and sharing my goals has helped me to define better goals for 2022. This post is a brief retrospective on the 2021 part of my journey, and the lessons I hope to have learned for the road ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thumbs.gfycat.com/NauticalPastLadybird-size_restricted.gif&#34; title=&#34;Carry on ...&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-did-your-year-go&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How did your year go?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those were my 2021 stretch goals and the tally I drew at the end of the year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Final tally, not too bad:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;✅ Spend 500 h on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kaggle?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Kaggle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;✅ Join 4 competitions and team up in 2 of them&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;✅ Publish 52 episodes of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/KaggleHiddenGems?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#KaggleHiddenGems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;❌ Write 12 blog posts&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;✅ Run my 1st marathon&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;❌ Do 1 muscle up&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;✅ Sleep 8 h/night&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Martin Henze (Heads or Tails) (@heads0rtai1s) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/heads0rtai1s/status/1476293217779920901?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;December 29, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that 2021 was year two of a global plague, it might be fair to add ‘having survived all that’ to the list of accomplishments. But I’m aware (and grateful) of my priviledged situation of being able to work from home on my computer, so let’s not cheapen the accomplishments of those who actually were out there working hard and who managed to stave off (or overcome) serious illness. A bit of perspective is necessary, from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think it is important to highlight the degree of structure and control that can be provided by setting goals and trying to reach them; however much arbitrary or insignificant those goals might appear in the bigger picture. I believe that especially in uncertain times there is a lot of comfort in wrestling a modicum of control from the chaotic universe. As long as we do the best we can do to our abilities (and circumstances) then we’re doing rather well. But enough existentialism. Let’s get back to data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the goals themselves, I’d like to go into more detail than the Twitter thread allowed. I’d like to emphasise that those are stretch goals, and that I didn’t expect to reach all of them. Wouldn’t be fun it were too easy, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;spend-500-hours-on-kaggle&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Spend 500 hours on Kaggle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success.&lt;/strong&gt; Now, hours themselves don’t create mastery; it’s about what you do during those hours that counts. A short time of focussed effort counts for more than a much longer period of distracted dabbling. Having said that: setting a specific goal that translates to 1-2 hours per day can help immensely in creating habits and budgeting time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the latter, I would often spend about 1 hour per day on Kaggle problems during the week, and 2 or 3 hours on the weekend. Calling it a (Kaggle) day after that helped to avoid the temptation of working later at night, especially during the week. Kaggle challenges are more akin to a marathon (&lt;em&gt;foreshadowing …&lt;/em&gt;) than a sprint, which means that pacing yourself becomes important. In general, having a healthy work-life balance is necessary to avoid burn out and loss of motivation (or health).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The habit-building effect of having a specific goal can hardly be overstated. Continuity is one of the main factors of successful learning and growing. If you’re spending (almost) every day on a certain project, or practicing a specific tool, then you are bound to make at least some progress in understanding. And learning is what Kaggle is mostly about, for me. (And the &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/&#34;&gt;community&lt;/a&gt;, of course.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;join-4-competition-and-team-up-in-2-of-them&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Join 4 competition and team up in 2 of them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success.&lt;/strong&gt; This continues the previous train of thought: competiting is less about the ranks and medals, but more a motivation for learning new skills and tools. I always found it most efficient to learn by doing - and to learn from examples and applications. Instead of merely reading books of theory, or even code, I prefered to focus on the skills that I needed to solve a specific problem. And what better challenge to spend 3 months at a time competing with the brightest applied-ML minds on Kaggle on a new and exiting problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021, I participated earnestly in 5 competitions. I also briefly dabbled in a few others; but honestly less is more in this kind of situation. You want to focus on one thing at a time, instead of scattering your attention across lots of projects and not really devoting enough time to any of them. I know, the temptation is great to jump into every new competition that launches. I’m trying myself to recover from that; so I recommend you do as I say, not do as I do. Having said that, 2021 for me was a notable improvement over previous year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the learning effect on Kaggle comes from reading other people’s contributions in form of Notebooks or Discussion posts. This kind of effect is applified by a factor of a lot when you team up with other competitors. I had only done this very occasionally in the past. The main reason was probably that I didn’t have enough confidence in my own skills to contribute meaningfully to a team. I don’t want to be carried. I want to make a significant difference. Having learnt a bit more in 2020 I decided to get outside of my comfort zone and challenge myself in a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a very fun and rewarding experience. I joined forces with my Kaggle buddy &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/YassineAlouini&#34;&gt;Yassine&lt;/a&gt; on 2 imaging competitions and learned a lot from him on deep learning architectures and training strategies. On the way, I became much more confident in using the high-level &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fast.ai/&#34;&gt;FastAI&lt;/a&gt; framework and also &lt;a href=&#34;https://colab.research.google.com&#34;&gt;Google Colab&lt;/a&gt;, which is a great cloud environment for GPU notebooks. Read my mid-2020 review on cloud GPUs &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2021/08/24/colab-plus-kaggle-cloud-gpu/&#34;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt;. Bottom line: there are lots of great things to be found in the clouds these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media0.giphy.com/media/3oEdv6UTqzNk9Y5i36/giphy.gif?cid=790b76119299a8b65e0c47548fe0e8dbd2d4ca4fefe9698e&amp;amp;rid=giphy.gif&amp;amp;ct=g%20...&#34; title=&#34;Burgers not included in the Colab Pro Plus subscription ... yet&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;publish-52-episodes-of-kaggle-hidden-gems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Publish 52 episodes of Kaggle Hidden Gems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success.&lt;/strong&gt; The Hidden Gems series is my attempt to give back something to the Kaggle community by discovering and promoting underrated Notebooks published on the platform. The Kaggle community has grown enormously over the last years. So many bright people from many walks of life contribute to the community; which is great because you have the chance to learn from them. One difficulty, though, of this higher volume of contributions is that sometimes great content can have difficulties standing out and being recognised for its quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every week I pick 3 new, underrated Notebooks to highlight. Here’s the most recent example at the time of writing: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/general/300228&#34;&gt;episode number 88&lt;/a&gt;. As a result my week doesn’t feel complete now without reading cool
Kaggle Notebooks. In 2021 I succesfuly managed to establish a continuity of one episode every Tuesday, without fail. 52 episodes in 52 weeks. On the occasion of episode 50, I gathered all the Gems data into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/headsortails/notebooks-of-the-week-hidden-gems&#34;&gt;Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt; and put together a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/headsortails/hidden-gems-a-collection-of-underrated-notebooks/&#34;&gt;Starter Notebook&lt;/a&gt;. This is Kaggle, after all, where even the data has data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;write-12-blog-posts&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Write 12 blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fail.&lt;/strong&gt; I only wrote 2 posts in total in 2021 (after writing 9 in 2019, and 5 in 2020). Establishing and keeping up a blogging habit is a question of time, certainly. But in my case, it might also be a challenge of perfectionism and preference for long posts. Like this post here, which is already shaping up to be longer than I had intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going out of my comfort zone when it comes to writing isn’t easy at all. I don’t expect a large audience for this blog. I’m writing mostly for myself, so that I can remember and digest some of the things that I picked up over time. At the same time, I want for anyone who stumbles across those posts to get some quality information out of reading them. And that holds me back from publishing more frequent and shorter posts. That is one lesson learnt from 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;run-my-1st-marathon&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Run my 1st marathon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success.&lt;/strong&gt; I gotta be honest: this is probably my proudest achievement. My first ever marathon. 42 km in one go. After failing a few attempts during the year, I finally got there on Dec 6th. Just in time to make it a 2021 achievement; but in time nonetheless. Running in colder weather was also more conducive to success, as opposed to my summer attempt in August. Who would have guessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, exercise has always been a way to destress and detach from coding and data analysis work, which isn’t the most physically active of all occupations. As such, I didn’t come cold into this marathon challenge but have a certain level of fitness that I’ve built and maintained over the years. When the pandemic started, running outdoors was one of the few exercises that I felt comfortable doing. Having never ran more than 10 km at a time before (and that was quite a few years ago), I then gradually worked up to this marathon challenge. From 5k to 10k, and then running my first half-marathon (21 km) in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t read a lot of running blogs or stuff, so some of the things I discovered for myself might have been easier to read up on, in hindsight. None of this is expert recommendation, obviously. One insight is that a full marathon is a very different beast from a half-marathon. The 21 km of the half-marathon are something that I could run without stopping or nutrition; even without water (although that might not be generally recommended). None of that worked for me for the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that after 2-ish hours of continuous exercise you have burned through most of your carb reserves (i.e. glycogen). I genuinely didn’t know that. Coincidentally, my longest non-stop exercises thus far were just under the 2h limit (and years ago). So, in my first past 30-km attempt I had to stop with leg cramps and fatigue, and it took me a couple hours and a good meal to recover from that. I later found out about that glycogen limit and that I had literally ran out of energy to burn. Fun times. So for the next attempts I got some energy gels plus water with electrolytes and it made a huge difference. Almost no issues after the successful marathon. Just the fun of walking up and down stairs for the days after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In numbers: I ran a total of 1332 km in 2021, which translates to about 1/30th around the earth, in 116 hours. I also logged about 3.7 million steps, for an average of about 10k steps per day. As a data addict, I’m using a Garmin watch and app for all those measurements. No link, since they haven’t given me a sponsorship yet. Gotta keep running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media4.giphy.com/media/9rRacglGbs68E/giphy.gif?cid=ecf05e472rkl4hg798m9nz6ikhrrr7nh9snqzkicv67yti1i&amp;amp;rid=giphy.gif&amp;amp;ct=g&#34; title=&#34;And running. And running.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;do-1-muscle-up&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Do 1 muscle up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fail.&lt;/strong&gt; Another failure. I didn’t even get close. I did pull-ups frequently, after my shorter runs, but couldn’t get a rhythm going. Another excuse is that I lost access to a decent pull-up bar early in the year, so that I had to make do with the crossbars of small football goals or with playground structures, both of which always have bars that are at the very least slightly too thick to grab them comfortably. If they’re not weirdly shaped to begin with. I’m sure that everyone knows exactly what I’m talking about. Very frequent situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my eternal optimism, I had also hoped to finish the marathon by mid year. And then focus on the muscle up afterwards. As it turned out, that didn’t quite work either; what with me needing until December to run the marathon and all. So, the muscle up needed more effort due to the conditions not being as ideal, which was more than I could do at the time. Another reason for the failure was poor planning, as I didn’t look for specific muscle-up progressions that would take me there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sleep-8-hnight&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sleep 8 h/night&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success.&lt;/strong&gt; This was likely the most important aspect. Sleep and rest are super important. We can only burn the midnight oil for so long before it has bad consequences for our mental and physical well-being. Balance is vital. I was very happy to reach and exceed my goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even though I got an average 8.4h over the year, there remained a notable variance of about 1 hour. I sometimes had to make up for shorter nights with sleeping longer at other times. I’m far from being an expert on sleep science, but from what I have read I believe that consistency is needed for building and maintaining healthy sleep patterns and restful recovery. Those patterns of mine still need some work, as the variations in sleep and wake times were also larger than I would have wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to end this post here. Originally, I was planning to put 2021 results and 2022 goals in the same post, but this one is pretty long already. See the lesson above on failing to write frequent and short posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up: how I’m building on these experiences for my 2022 journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Astronomy to Data Science - A Travel Journal</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/09/19/first-six-months/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/09/19/first-six-months/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The first six months as a Data Scientist have gone by in a blur of new tools, techniques, and experiences. In my new job, I’m lucky to be (once again) part of a great team of people who are not just smart, but always happy to share their knowledge and feedback in a productive and thoughtful way. A supportive environment helps a lot. &lt;em&gt;Surprising insight - I know.&lt;/em&gt; Worth repeating nonetheless. Now it’s time to look back and reflect on the main challenges and lessons learnt during this initial stage in my journey from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/search/fq=%7B!type%3Daqp%20v%3D%24fq_database%7D&amp;amp;fq_database=database%3A%20astronomy&amp;amp;q=author%3A(%22Henze%2C%20Martin%22)&amp;amp;sort=date%20desc%2C%20bibcode%20desc&amp;amp;p_=0&#34;&gt;Academic Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/martin-henze&#34;&gt;Data Science in the Real World&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/55gMT6FcZiOHiauVt8/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;It&amp;#39;s not just fantasy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is mainly aimed at astronomers who are interested in making the switch. &lt;em&gt;As always, I’m doing a stellar job in choosing the largest possible target audience.&lt;/em&gt; Still, I think that my thoughts might also be interesting for other academics, young students, or anyone interested in Data Science or Machine Learning. &lt;em&gt;Yeah…, that should cover enough people to propel my fame.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let’s start with the tools of the trade:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming languages:&lt;/strong&gt; If you want to learn one language then learn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/about/gettingstarted/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;. And that’s a hard thing for me to write, because personally I prefer the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/online-learning/#r-programming&#34;&gt;R language&lt;/a&gt; with its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt; collection of packages. But Python has a lot going for it: firstly, it has the appeal of being a general purpose programming language and as such is accessible to a vast audience from many different backgrounds. Secondly, it also has an immense repository of specialised libraries. For instance, in astrophysics we have the great &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.astropy.org&#34;&gt;astropy&lt;/a&gt; package. For Machine Learning basics there’s the ubiquitous &lt;a href=&#34;https://scikit-learn.org/&#34;&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt;. And thirdly: a lot of cutting-edge methods from Neural Network research are being quickly ported into Python frameworks. Those factors mean that today most Data Science teams communicate in Python, and this trend is likely to continue in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Straight talk: R is a powerful language but it’s a bit more idiosyncratic (with a somewhat steeper learning curve) and currently less widely used, which gives Python the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/headsortails/what-we-do-in-the-kernels-a-kaggle-survey-story&#34;&gt;edge in popularity&lt;/a&gt;. And now is a crucial time for popularity to drive adoption: &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.blog/2017/09/06/incredible-growth-python/&#34;&gt;Both R and Python are growing&lt;/a&gt;, yet Python’s growth is exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectively, R can do everything that Python can do (including e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://tensorflow.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;Tensorflow&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://keras.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;Keras&lt;/a&gt; wrappers). Many things it can do better, such as beautiful visualisations (e.g. with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-graph-gallery.com/ggplot2-package.html&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;) or all the statistics you could possibly ever need in your life. Sometimes it might do things a little slower. But if you really need speed then native Python won’t cut it either. I digress. More importantly: astronomers: forget about IDL. Outside astronomy, no one even knows it exists - and all that legacy code is a weakness rather than a strength. MATLAB is not very popular either. Forget about Fortran (unless you want to write your own Deep Learning Nets or Gradient Boosted Trees). Some C might come in handy. And certainly forget about IRAF and MIDAS. &lt;em&gt;A lot of 80s things are back in fashion but even nostalgia has its limits.&lt;/em&gt; Even if you plan to stay in academia, do your career a favour and learn Python. If you have the resources, learn R and Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/3o7aCRloybJlXpNjSU/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;See also the next post...&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data bases:&lt;/strong&gt; You will need at least basic skills in one data query language; ideally advanced skills in several ones to boost your productivity. An SQL flavour will be very useful; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sqlite.org/&#34;&gt;those&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mysql.com/&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.postgresql.org/&#34;&gt;relatively&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/sql-server/default.aspx&#34;&gt;similar&lt;/a&gt; and transitions between them will be easy. NoSQL tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elastic.co/products/elasticsearch&#34;&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt; can be required, too. Some astrophysics projects have used these frameworks for a while, but in my field we mainly relied on sending fits files back and forth. Having well-designed data base schemata is an immense advantage. Almost all industry jobs will involve the &lt;em&gt;Notorious BFD (Big Freaking Data)&lt;/em&gt; - which will be stored in those very data bases. The more of data selection, cleaning, and merging you can do on those servers, the more efficient is your work. This also includes software like &lt;a href=&#34;https://spark.apache.org/&#34;&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt;. Successful data preparation is more than half the battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environments:&lt;/strong&gt; Most people in Data Science use &lt;a href=&#34;https://jupyter.org&#34;&gt;Jupyter Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; to share Exploratory Data Analysis, code samples, or proof of concept software snippets. I know that those tools have already achieved some popularity in Astronomy, but it’s worth emphasising how valuable they are for analysing data as a team. As an R user, in addition to using Jupyter, you can have an even smoother experience with &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;Rmarkdown&lt;/a&gt; - ideally in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; which I can strongly recommend as an IDE. Here is also a good place to mention version control: &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; has become the most popular tool, and places like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.gitlab.com&#34;&gt;gitlab&lt;/a&gt; provide convenient hosting space. These shared spaces are pretty much indispensable for having multiple people working on the same project, but even for your individual projects &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; is well worth the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codecademy.com/learn/learn-git&#34;&gt;couple hours investment to learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, let’s talk about workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Science projects&lt;/strong&gt; can span from a few hours to several weeks. They can also involve only yourself, several data scientists, or other parts of the company such as software engineering or sales. Which aspects dominate depends on your actual position in the team and on your company’s business. Similarly, you can spend different amounts of your time on data cleaning, exploratory analysis, visualisation, or machine learning. In my case, projects typically last weeks - with the occasional request for a couple of hours or days. Coming from an observational astrophysics field focussed on transient sources, I was already used to quickly switching my attention to a new project (when an interesting nova eruption was found). There are obvious parallels here in the shape of client requests, news stories, financial IPOs or similar (semi-) unexpected events that warrant immediate attention. Multi-tasking is important. Month-long projects are rare. The iteration loops are much quicker than what I had known in academia. It’s a bit of a cliché by now, but you really want to fail fast. Time is of the essence and it rarely seems to move linearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/efU9WbFkGP9NAkLOWn/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Trust me; I am a doctor&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time budgets:&lt;/strong&gt; Within a typical data science project, expect to spend more of your time on data cleaning and quality control than you would have liked. Probably upwards of 50%, including several iterations of identifying outliers and fixing data errors. Real-world data is considerably messier than astrophysical data. &lt;em&gt;Yes, that is possible.&lt;/em&gt; And yes: I have worked with multi-wavelength, multi-telescope projects that produced messy data. A random set of typical industry projects have less in common among them than their astronomical counterparts; and sources of uncertainty and systematics can be plentiful. Data exploration will take up another maybe 25% of your time, including visualisations. The remaining 25% will likely go towards documenting and communicating your findings. I’m including here the time it will take to include your results into a production environment. If you are aiming to be a Machine Learning engineer these tasks will take up a larger chunk of your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soft skills:&lt;/strong&gt; Let me stress that it is a valuable and non-trivial skill to be able to communicate your results clearly and succinctly to a variety of audiences. Your team members will care about which statistical tests you used - management or clients will probably not. At academic conferences, we’ve all sat through those presentations that had slides upon slides filled with text and equations and intricate findings, yet little mention of the bigger picture or what can be learned from it. This is what you want to avoid - &lt;em&gt;both as a speaker and an audience member, incidentally.&lt;/em&gt; Adjust your slides to your audience. Together with (well-documented) code samples, the major deliverable of your project is an efficient communication of its results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus concludes this communication of my impressions and experiences; at least for the moment. There will be more detailed updates on certain key aspects as time progresses. Let’s see what the next 6 months will bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/4XPaiZh5DchLG/giphy.gif&#34; title=&#34;Well, next week. Hopefully.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I’m trying out &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt; as a sarcasm/humour indicator. Since written text has no tone; and so on. &lt;em&gt;But I’m sure that was abundantly clear from context.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prologue</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/08/prologue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/08/prologue/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;This one is all about &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;. In many ways life is about change. Not all change is good, but without it there would be no evolution. No progress. And as much as we sometimes want certain moments to last, stagnation is rarely a good thing. Without attempting something new it is impossible to say whether it will succeed. I guess that’s a verbose way of saying: I decided to start a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog is far from the only change, though. After a good ten years of working in astronomy and astrophysics I have just made the transition into data science. Instead of exploding stars in nearby galaxies I will now be working on topics that are much closer to our every day experience; such as travel, consumer trends, or demographics. Yeah, this is a bigger change than the blog. Maybe I should have led with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reasons for changing careers are manifold. First and foremost I’m driven by curiosity. I want to understand the world, and beyond, and figure out how everything works. What motivates people, makes economies flourish, or lightens up entire suns like a cosmic firework. And after gazing out into the universe for quite some time, maybe it is time to work a little closer to home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my field of academia, anything beyond a traditional research career is still regarded as a somewhat unusual alternative path; even though only a small percentage of astrophysics PhDs will end up in a tenured (professor) position at a university. Thus, I hope that these Chronicles of an Astronomer’s Adventures in Data Science (hopefully the title of the eventual movie; take note Hollywood) will be useful for other young astronomers who are contemplating their career options. Or it might even make them aware of the fact that they have career options. Academia, for all it’s advantages, can still be rather insular and does not always do the best job in emphasising transferable skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And many astronomers have a whole bag of skills they can transfer. Observational astronomers, like me, turns out are rather good at analysing data. Sometimes big data, often messy data. Different telescopes can have very different ways of data collection and storage. I might share some X-ray imaging data in a future throwback post. While a typical astronomer’s education focusses heavily on the (astro-) physics and the specific instrument software, many of us have taught themselves programming, statistics, data bases, or other useful things practically on the side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to another of my motivations: to understand the tools that help us understand the world. I’m a big fan of data visualisation to extract its secrets and hidden insights. There will be many pictures here; hopefully some pretty ones among them. And while the best tool for a certain job might be a very specific one, many tools are surprisingly versatile. Languages like Python and R. Data base tools like the various SQL flavours. Data viz libraries like ggplot2, matplotlib, or D3. Those will be among the frequent Dramatis Personae in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will aim for at least weekly posts, describing my impressions of working in data science and the contrast to academia. I’ll give it a decent try not to reveal any industry secrets. There aren’t really many “academia secrets”, since everything interesting get published sooner rather than later. I guess that’s one contrast. There will be the occassional update about new astro results, some throwback posts, and any other insights I find noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world, after all, is always changing. I was born in East Germany when it was still a separate country - locked in ideological contest with its western brother. When I was a kid, a peaceful revolution swept away the old, out-of-touch system and then, from one day to the next, the borders were open and change was as fundamental as it was inevitable. Down the line, this taught me that there aren’t many things you can take for granted, but as long as you are prepared for change and willing to adapt there can be much potential in every new twist and turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is where I come from. Now let’s see what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
