<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kaggle on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>/tags/kaggle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kaggle on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/kaggle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Colab Pro&#43; Features, Kaggling on Colab, and Cloud GPU Platforms</title>
      <link>/2021/08/24/colab-plus-kaggle-cloud-gpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/08/24/colab-plus-kaggle-cloud-gpu/</guid>
      <description>In the final, hectic days of a recent Kaggle competition I found myself in want of more GPU power. As one often does in such an occasion. My own laptop, with its GPU setup, was doing a fine job with various small models and small images, but scaling up both aspects became necessary to climb the leaderboard further. My first choice options GCP and AWS quickly turned out to require quota increases which either didn’t happen or took too long.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animations in the time of Coronavirus</title>
      <link>/2020/04/30/animate-map-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/30/animate-map-covid/</guid>
      <description>The first four months of 2020 have been dominated by the Coronavirus pandemic (aka COVID-19), which has transformed global life in an unprecedented way. Societies and economies struggle to adapt to the new conditions and necessary contraints. A reassuringly large fraction of governments around the world continue to take evidence-based approaches to this crisis that are grounded in large scale data collection efforts. Most of this data is being made publicly available and can be studied in real time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes a community great?</title>
      <link>/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/</guid>
      <description>The easy answer to this question is: the people. Great people build great communities. Case not quite closed yet, though, because there is more to it. Even the most promising group of individuals needs certain conditions in order to grow into a strong and thriving community. The kind of community that lifts up its members beyond their individual capabilities and becomes more than the sum of their proverbial skills and contributions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>