<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>community on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/categories/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in community on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/categories/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing a Kaggle Notebooks Competition</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/04/19/gems-comp-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/04/19/gems-comp-design/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I launched my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/discussions/general/317093&#34;&gt;first very own competition on the Kaggle platform&lt;/a&gt;, the goal of which is to design engaging data science notebooks with great visuals, narration, and insights. Today, at the half-way point of the competition, I want to write about my motivations for creating this challenge, the underlying data, and my criteria of what makes a captivating and accessible notebook in the R or Python languages. All of this is strongly connected to what I see as one of the most underrated skills in the fields of data science (DS) and machine learning (ML): the ability to effectively communicate your approach and your findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s start at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-hidden-gems-project&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Hidden Gems project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was two years ago when, out of a whim and a chat on Twitter, I’ve decided that it was time to put a spotlight on the underrated content found within the Kaggle community. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com&#34;&gt;Kaggle platform&lt;/a&gt; has grown dramatically over the last years, and so has the number of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code&#34;&gt;Kaggle Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. Jupyter or Rmarkdown analysis notebooks of competitions, datasets, tutorials, dataviz challenges, and more. One of the great strengths of the Kaggle platform is the ability to run those notebooks in their cloud environment; complete with free compute, GPU &amp;amp; TPU time, a pre-installed DS &amp;amp; ML stack, and access to tons of different datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, such a powerful environment, together with a supportive yet competitive community, produces a lot of great content. There are many notebooks on Kaggle that for good reasons are very popular: they explain state-of-the-art ML approaches, present new modelling ideas, enlighten us with detailed data explorations, or showcase carefully crafted visuals. But at the same time there are also notebooks that have a high quality yet, for whichever reason, haven’t received many views, upvotes, or feedback. The Hidden Gems project is my attempt to rectify this situation. I wanted to do my little bit in helping to get those notebooks and their authors the attention that they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/general/150603&#34;&gt;very beginning&lt;/a&gt;, my goal with this series has been to showcase underrated Kaggle Notebooks and to illuminate the diversity and creativity of the community. My selections are always highly subjective; reflecting my own views and preferences. And I always encourage the readers of the series to further engage with the community by posting about other underestimated Notebooks in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-reason-to-celebrate&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Reason to Celebrate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years, I managed to keep up a cadence of posting about three underrated notebooks per week; every week. On each Tuesday, without fail, I would publish a new episode of Hidden Gems on Kaggle and on social media. I’ve learnt a lot during this time from all the notebooks that I’ve reviewed. And reading new and interesting works has become an integral part of my week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were notable milestones on the way: for episode 50 I’ve created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/headsortails/notebooks-of-the-week-hidden-gems&#34;&gt;dedicated Kaggle dataset of all my Hidden Gems episodes&lt;/a&gt; together with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/headsortails/hidden-gems-a-collection-of-underrated-notebooks&#34;&gt;Starter Notebook written in tidyverse R&lt;/a&gt;. The notebook also drew connections to the comprehensive &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/kaggle/meta-kaggle&#34;&gt;Meta Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt;, where Kaggle publishes all the meta data about the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on Tuesday April 5th 2022 my little series reached its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/discussions/general/317093&#34;&gt;100th episode&lt;/a&gt;! I’m still pretty amazed at this significant milestone; and at the fact that Kagglers have continued to visit and appreciate my episodes throughout those one hundred weeks. This definitely called for a celebration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I much prefer to celebrate with my fellow Kagglers, so on the very same day I launched a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/discussions/general/317093&#34;&gt;surprise competition&lt;/a&gt; aimed at exploring the Hidden Gems data and its connections to related datasets. Over the preceding weeks and months, I had managed to put together a stellar panel of judges to evaluate the submissions and to obtain cool swag prizes (and more!) from Kaggle itself and from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wandb.ai/site&#34;&gt;Weights &amp;amp; Biases platform&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks so much for sponsoring this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to emphasize that in the design of this competition I drew on inspiration from the different judges, especially from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bhutanisanyam1&#34;&gt;Sanyam Bhutani&lt;/a&gt;, the host of the popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/c/chaitimedatascience&#34;&gt;Chai Time Data Science podcast&lt;/a&gt;, who had hosted his own &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rohanrao/chai-time-data-science&#34;&gt;Notebooks competition&lt;/a&gt; back in 2020. I got a lot of ideas from that competition and I’m grateful to Sanyam and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/rohanrao&#34;&gt;Rohan Rao&lt;/a&gt; for organising it and inviting me to the panel of judges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the Hidden Gems competition is to help people learn and practice how to craft engaging and insightful DS &amp;amp; ML presentations. All contributions are guaranteed to receive an evaluation and constructive feedback from a panel of highly experienced Kaggle community members. Below this overview infographic I share instructions on how to join, as well as my advice on the important elements of a successful notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../static/pics/hidden_gems_competition.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hidden Gems Competition poster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;evaluation-criteria-what-makes-a-great-notebook&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Evaluation Criteria: What makes a great notebook?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a typical Kaggle competition with predictions that are scored on a leaderboard. Instead, &lt;em&gt;submissions are Kaggle Notebooks&lt;/em&gt;. Anyone can participate simply by creating a public Notebook on the Hidden Gems dataset. All submission will be evaluated by a panel of expert judges on five specific criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the criteria which I see as the cornerstones of communicating accessible ML &amp;amp; DS insights. Here is a list explaining each criterion, in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality of data visuals:&lt;/strong&gt; How clean, well designed, and approachable are the visualisations? Does the type of visualisation match the kind of insight that is being communicated? Are there consistent styles or colour schemes?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Narration &amp;amp; storytelling:&lt;/strong&gt; Is the analysis well explained and documented to allow the reader to understand insights and their context? Does the notebook follow an engaging flow? Are there certain narrative tools that make the work stand out?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure &amp;amp; presentation:&lt;/strong&gt; Are the different parts of the notebook well defined? How do those parts relate to one another? Is the code clean? Are the key insights centered, but the code and context easily accessible?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality of insights:&lt;/strong&gt; Are the insights relevant, useful, and actionable? Does the notebook tell us something new, unexpected, or counter intuitive? Does the work contain recommendations or predictions for the future?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creativity &amp;amp; originality:&lt;/strong&gt; How novel and inventive are the ideas and approach? Am I positively surprised by some stylistic choices or discovered findings? Does the author have their own style, and perhaps take some design risks in expressing it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might notice that those criteria have a strong overlap with best practices in data journalism. Which makes sense, because the goals are very similar: to clearly present a cohesive narrative that is insightful and accessible to an audience. Like for many ways of communicating, the details here depend on who your audience is and what kind of findings your are communicating. The Kaggle community is likely more technically inclined than most, so you could decide to put a strong emphasis on well documented data wrangling or model architectures. Or you could hide all the code in your notebook and rely on a strong narrative with a few hand-crafted visuals. Like in a good piece of popular data journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-join&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to join&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you share my passion for dataviz and storytelling, then you might now be interested to know how you can join this competition to practice your skills and win some prizes. You might even consider to join the Kaggle platform just to compete in this challenge, in which case I’d be very honoured. This might be a good time to mention that there is a special prize category for people who will have written their very first Kaggle notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To join, go to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/headsortails/notebooks-of-the-week-hidden-gems/discussion/317098&#34;&gt;dataset page&lt;/a&gt;. At the very top, you will find a button that says “New Notebook”. Click that, and choose between Python or R (and R Jupyter notebook or Rmarkdown). You will find yourself in the Kaggle editor, where the dataset is already available, and start exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to watch some examples of what can be done with the dataset and how to use the Kaggle editor, here are a few live streams done by the members of the judge panel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o__J3bkp2PQ&#34;&gt;The launch stream by Sanyam Bhutani and myself&lt;/a&gt; - where we explain the background and setup of the competition in detail. I go through my starter notebook, and Sanyam shows how to connect to the Weights &amp;amp; Biases platform.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J2iLOkIqwQo&#34;&gt;Stream on Abhishek Thakur’s youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; - focussing on overall EDA advice and how to write engaging notebooks. We answer quite a few questions from the audience and talk about the notebook that won the first weekly price.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.twitch.tv/videos/1449472244&#34;&gt;Live coding with Rob Mulla on twitch&lt;/a&gt; - a more in-depth chat about motivations and various EDA techniques in R and Python. I’m explaining my R starter notebook and Rob starts a live EDA in Python.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o-Cefl_zLEk&#34;&gt;Live coding EDA by Andrada Olteanu hosted by Sanyam Bhutani&lt;/a&gt; - full of great advice for notebook design and dataviz crafting. Andrada starts a live EDA in Python.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kaggle editor works pretty well for Jupyter-style notebooks. When it comes to Rmarkdown content, I prefer to build it locally in Rstudio and then copy/paste my work into the Kaggle environment and run it there (button “Save Version”). This way, you can take advantage of all the Rstudio tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this post got you interested in joining the ongoing competition to practice your skills when it comes to EDA and notebook design. I would love to see your ideas and creativity! And to reward them with some cool swag prizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/headsortails/notebooks-of-the-week-hidden-gems/discussion/317098&#34;&gt;You can join here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing tweets with the rtweet package</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/20/rtweet-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/20/rtweet-intro/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/rmarkdown-libs/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a brief post on collecting and analysing tweets. I will show how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/rtweet&#34;&gt;rtweet&lt;/a&gt; package to extract Twitter posts about the R community. This ties into last weeks post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/&#34;&gt;rstudio::conf and community values&lt;/a&gt;, and is also related to my previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/01/23/rvest-intro-astro/&#34;&gt;intro post on web scraping&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we load &lt;code&gt;rtweet&lt;/code&gt; and other (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;) packages we will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;libs &amp;lt;- c(&amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;tibble&amp;#39;,      # wrangling
          &amp;#39;stringr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;rtweet&amp;#39;,    # strings, tweets
          &amp;#39;knitr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;kableExtra&amp;#39;,  # table styling
          &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39;,            # time
          &amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;ggthemes&amp;#39;)  # plots
invisible(lapply(libs, library, character.only = TRUE))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use the &lt;code&gt;rtweet&lt;/code&gt; package you need a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; account and the package needs to be authorised to access that account. The authorisation process is very smooth: just run a command like the one below and an authorisation tab will open in your browser (via &lt;code&gt;rstats2twitter&lt;/code&gt;). Approving the authorisation will store a credential token on your machine (called &lt;code&gt;.rtweet_token.rds&lt;/code&gt;) for a all future requests. This token should end up safe in your home directory, but you might still want to double check that it doesn’t get pushed to any public github repos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how we search for recent tweets about “rstats” + “community”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt &amp;lt;- search_tweets(
  &amp;quot;rstats community&amp;quot;, n = 1000, include_rts = FALSE
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the search string, white space acts like “AND” and order doesn’t matter. To search for either term (inclusive) you can use “OR”. To search for specific sequences of terms wrap them in single quotes (e.g. ‘rstats community’). The &lt;code&gt;search_tweets&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/rtweet/versions/0.7.0/topics/search_tweets&#34;&gt;help page&lt;/a&gt; has further and more detailed query instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: the free Twitter API only allows you to access tweets from the last 6-9 days.&lt;/strong&gt; For anything more you need a paid API. I was originally planning to search for &lt;code&gt;#rstudioconf&lt;/code&gt; tweets, but the conference is 3 weeks ago now. So I guess that’s what I get for taking so long with this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter’s &lt;em&gt;request limit is 18k tweets per 15 minute interval&lt;/em&gt;. To download more tweets in one go you can set the parameter &lt;code&gt;retryonratelimit = TRUE&lt;/code&gt;, but you would have to wait 15 min for the retry. This is a convenience function, so that you don’t need to run individual 18k queries and stack them together by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;search_tweets&lt;/code&gt; we can derive pretty much all the information about a tweet, its author, and any quoted tweets: the full text, retweet count, hashtags, mentions, author bio; you name it. A total of 90 columns. Not all of them will always have values, but it looks like a very comprehensive set of features to me. Here is a small subset of those features: the date-time of the tweet (in UT), the user name, and the number of followers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt %&amp;gt;% 
  select(tweeted = created_at,
         screen_name,
         followers = followers_count) %&amp;gt;% 
  head(5) %&amp;gt;% 
  kable() %&amp;gt;% 
  column_spec(1:3, width = c(&amp;quot;45%&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;35%&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;20%&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  kable_styling()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;table&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
tweeted
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
screen_name
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
followers
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 18:32:47
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
danicassol
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
157
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 17:51:03
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
LK_Fitzpatrick
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
511
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 17:40:19
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
PyData
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
48209
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 16:34:52
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
rOpenSci
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
28207
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 13:24:03
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
GiusCalamita
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
38
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll conclude with some (small number) statistics about “rstats” “community” posts. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://rtweet.info/&#34;&gt;rtweet docs&lt;/a&gt; include many more examples and inspiration for projects. This is the frequency of tweets over the last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(date = date(created_at)) %&amp;gt;% 
  count(date) %&amp;gt;% 
  ggplot(aes(date, n)) +
  geom_line(col = &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;) +
  labs(x = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;, y = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) +
  theme_fivethirtyeight() +
  theme(legend.position = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;) +
  ggtitle(&amp;quot;Daily number of tweets about the &amp;#39;rstats community&amp;#39;&amp;quot;,
          subtitle = &amp;quot;Extracted using the rtweet package&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/post/2020-02-20-rtweet-intro_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notable spike on Feb 12 was caused by &lt;code&gt;@kierisi&lt;/code&gt; asking about people’s experiences with the community. I’m looking forward to her blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m working on a presentation about the R Community (yes, yes I&amp;#39;ll make a blog post!) and while I have *my* opinions, I&amp;#39;d really love to showcase your experiences!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What motivated you to join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; community? Why do you participate? What makes you stay?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(DMs are OK, too!) &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/7h3xKZ0Cg2&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/7h3xKZ0Cg2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jesse Mostipak 🦦 (@kierisi) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kierisi/status/1227666597860577281?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 12, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rstudio::conf retrospective</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I was fortunate to attend my very first &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/conference/&#34;&gt;Rstudio conference&lt;/a&gt;. Spoiler: it was an amazing event - packed to the brim with new ideas, tools, impressions, and most important of all: smart and kind people. This was the first time that San Francisco was hosting “rstudio::conf” (the affectionate shorthand is mirroring R’s package::tool syntax). Having moved to the Bay Area not long ago I really counted myself lucky to have such a promising event in my neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written about the importance of a strong and supportive community once before: in &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/&#34;&gt;last year’s post&lt;/a&gt; on meeting my favourite &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com&#34;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; crowd for the first time in real life. The rstudio::conf confirmed my belief that progress in any field is greatly boosted by having friendly and competent people around to support you and lift you up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/pics/rstudioconf20_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rstudio::conf opening; with about 20% of the audience visible&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;rstudio::conf opening; with about 20% of the audience visible&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing exemplifies this attitude better than the way in which the R community has embraced the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ericholscher.com/blog/2017/aug/2/pacman-rule-conferences/&#34;&gt;Pac-Man rule&lt;/a&gt;: “When standing as a group of people, always leave room for 1 person to join your group.” In other words, if you’re talking as a group then don’t stand in a closed circle but leave a bit of free space for anyone who’d like to participate in the conversation. At rstudio::conf I saw this concept work extremely well and it allowed me (and many others) to quickly connect with new people and have fun and inspiring conversations. It may have also helped that we all had at least one thing in common to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key aspect the R community excels in is to actively champion diversity and inclusion. This diversity within the community is mirrored by, and without a doubt contributes to, the richness and variety of the growing R ecosystem. In a tech sector that is still predominantly white and/or male, I strongly believe that the more a community welcomes all strata of society the better it can evolve and strive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the R universe, including the tidyverse, is growing rapidly indeed. I learned lots of new tricks from seasoned expeRts (like the unpacking operator &lt;code&gt;%&amp;lt;-%&lt;/code&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rdrr.io/cran/zeallot/man/operator.html&#34;&gt;zeallot package&lt;/a&gt;) and discovered so many cool packages I hadn’t been aware of. To name only three, in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HenrikBengtsson/future&#34;&gt;future&lt;/a&gt;: the promising heir to the popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/foreach/index.html&#34;&gt;foreach package&lt;/a&gt; in the parallel processing domain; developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HenrikBengtsson&#34;&gt;Henrik Bengtsson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EvaMaeRey/flipbookr&#34;&gt;flipbookr&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EvaMaeRey&#34;&gt;Gina Reynolds’&lt;/a&gt; side-by-side and step-by-step tool to illustrate how code turns into output. Great resource for teaching and demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidymodels/tune&#34;&gt;tune&lt;/a&gt;: the newest &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidymodels&#34;&gt;tidymodels&lt;/a&gt; family member; responsible for tuning hyperparameters. Presented by mastermind &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topepo&#34;&gt;Max Kuhn&lt;/a&gt;, it was great to see how the individual tidymodels components come together to soon form a powerful and consistent machine learning workflow. Exciting times ahead!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course the most important consequence of the healthy expansion of the R ecosystem is the existence of many new hex stickers ;-) . This was my first opportunity to become a hunter and gatherer of those colourful collectibles, and I managed to ultimately design a whole new look for my laptop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/pics/rstudioconf20_2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I’m gonna need a bigger laptop&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m gonna need a bigger laptop&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For all your R and Data Science needs check out the R for Data Science (R4DS) online learning community on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/R4DScommunity&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; and slack!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You’re probably not surprised to hear that there is an R package that lets you design your own hex stickers. It is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GuangchuangYu/hexSticker&#34;&gt;hexSticker&lt;/a&gt;. That name is probably even less surprising.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested to meet fellow R enthusiasts you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://jumpingrivers.github.io/meetingsR/&#34;&gt;find here&lt;/a&gt; a pretty comprehensive list of events and user groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
