<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>/categories/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/categories/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing tweets with the rtweet package</title>
      <link>/2020/02/20/rtweet-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/20/rtweet-intro/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a brief post on collecting and analysing tweets. I will show how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/rtweet&#34;&gt;rtweet&lt;/a&gt; package to extract Twitter posts about the R community. This ties into last weeks post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/&#34;&gt;rstudio::conf and community values&lt;/a&gt;, and is also related to my previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2020/01/23/rvest-intro-astro/&#34;&gt;intro post on web scraping&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we load &lt;code&gt;rtweet&lt;/code&gt; and other (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;) packages we will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;libs &amp;lt;- c(&amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;tibble&amp;#39;,      # wrangling
          &amp;#39;stringr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;rtweet&amp;#39;,    # strings, tweets
          &amp;#39;knitr&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;kableExtra&amp;#39;,  # table styling
          &amp;#39;lubridate&amp;#39;,            # time
          &amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;ggthemes&amp;#39;)  # plots
invisible(lapply(libs, library, character.only = TRUE))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use the &lt;code&gt;rtweet&lt;/code&gt; package you need a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; account and the package needs to be authorised to access that account. The authorisation process is very smooth: just run a command like the one below and an authorisation tab will open in your browser (via &lt;code&gt;rstats2twitter&lt;/code&gt;). Approving the authorisation will store a credential token on your machine (called &lt;code&gt;.rtweet_token.rds&lt;/code&gt;) for a all future requests. This token should end up safe in your home directory, but you might still want to double check that it doesn’t get pushed to any public github repos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how we search for recent tweets about “rstats” + “community”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt &amp;lt;- search_tweets(
  &amp;quot;rstats community&amp;quot;, n = 1000, include_rts = FALSE
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the search string, white space acts like “AND” and order doesn’t matter. To search for either term (inclusive) you can use “OR”. To search for specific sequences of terms wrap them in single quotes (e.g. ‘rstats community’). The &lt;code&gt;search_tweets&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/rtweet/versions/0.7.0/topics/search_tweets&#34;&gt;help page&lt;/a&gt; has further and more detailed query instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: the free Twitter API only allows you to access tweets from the last 6-9 days.&lt;/strong&gt; For anything more you need a paid API. I was originally planning to search for &lt;code&gt;#rstudioconf&lt;/code&gt; tweets, but the conference is 3 weeks ago now. So I guess that’s what I get for taking so long with this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter’s &lt;em&gt;request limit is 18k tweets per 15 minute interval&lt;/em&gt;. To download more tweets in one go you can set the parameter &lt;code&gt;retryonratelimit = TRUE&lt;/code&gt;, but you would have to wait 15 min for the retry. This is a convenience function, so that you don’t need to run individual 18k queries and stack them together by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;search_tweets&lt;/code&gt; we can derive pretty much all the information about a tweet, its author, and any quoted tweets: the full text, retweet count, hashtags, mentions, author bio; you name it. A total of 90 columns. Not all of them will always have values, but it looks like a very comprehensive set of features to me. Here is a small subset of those features: the date-time of the tweet (in UT), the user name, and the number of followers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt %&amp;gt;% 
  select(tweeted = created_at,
         screen_name,
         followers = followers_count) %&amp;gt;% 
  head(5) %&amp;gt;% 
  kable() %&amp;gt;% 
  column_spec(1:3, width = c(&amp;quot;45%&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;35%&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;20%&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  kable_styling()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;table&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
tweeted
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
screen_name
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
followers
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 18:32:47
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
danicassol
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
157
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 17:51:03
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
LK_Fitzpatrick
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
511
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 17:40:19
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
PyData
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
48209
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 16:34:52
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
rOpenSci
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
28207
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
2020-02-20 13:24:03
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
GiusCalamita
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right;width: 45%; &#34;&gt;
38
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll conclude with some (small number) statistics about “rstats” “community” posts. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://rtweet.info/&#34;&gt;rtweet docs&lt;/a&gt; include many more examples and inspiration for projects. This is the frequency of tweets over the last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rt %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(date = date(created_at)) %&amp;gt;% 
  count(date) %&amp;gt;% 
  ggplot(aes(date, n)) +
  geom_line(col = &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;) +
  labs(x = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;, y = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) +
  theme_fivethirtyeight() +
  theme(legend.position = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;) +
  ggtitle(&amp;quot;Daily number of tweets about the &amp;#39;rstats community&amp;#39;&amp;quot;,
          subtitle = &amp;quot;Extracted using the rtweet package&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-02-20-rtweet-intro_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notable spike on Feb 12 was caused by &lt;code&gt;@kierisi&lt;/code&gt; asking about people’s experiences with the community. I’m looking forward to her blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m working on a presentation about the R Community (yes, yes I&amp;#39;ll make a blog post!) and while I have *my* opinions, I&amp;#39;d really love to showcase your experiences!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What motivated you to join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; community? Why do you participate? What makes you stay?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(DMs are OK, too!) &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/7h3xKZ0Cg2&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/7h3xKZ0Cg2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jesse Mostipak 🦦 (@kierisi) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kierisi/status/1227666597860577281?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 12, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rstudio::conf retrospective</title>
      <link>/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/13/rstudio-conf/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I was fortunate to attend my very first &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/conference/&#34;&gt;Rstudio conference&lt;/a&gt;. Spoiler: it was an amazing event - packed to the brim with new ideas, tools, impressions, and most important of all: smart and kind people. This was the first time that San Francisco was hosting “rstudio::conf” (the affectionate shorthand is mirroring R’s package::tool syntax). Having moved to the Bay Area not long ago I really counted myself lucky to have such a promising event in my neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written about the importance of a strong and supportive community once before: in &lt;a href=&#34;https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/&#34;&gt;last year’s post&lt;/a&gt; on meeting my favourite &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com&#34;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; crowd for the first time in real life. The rstudio::conf confirmed my belief that progress in any field is greatly boosted by having friendly and competent people around to support you and lift you up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/pics/rstudioconf20_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rstudio::conf opening; with about 20% of the audience visible&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;rstudio::conf opening; with about 20% of the audience visible&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing exemplifies this attitude better than the way in which the R community has embraced the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ericholscher.com/blog/2017/aug/2/pacman-rule-conferences/&#34;&gt;Pac-Man rule&lt;/a&gt;: “When standing as a group of people, always leave room for 1 person to join your group.” In other words, if you’re talking as a group then don’t stand in a closed circle but leave a bit of free space for anyone who’d like to participate in the conversation. At rstudio::conf I saw this concept work extremely well and it allowed me (and many others) to quickly connect with new people and have fun and inspiring conversations. It may have also helped that we all had at least one thing in common to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key aspect the R community excels in is to actively champion diversity and inclusion. This diversity within the community is mirrored by, and without a doubt contributes to, the richness and variety of the growing R ecosystem. In a tech sector that is still predominantly white and/or male, I strongly believe that the more a community welcomes all strata of society the better it can evolve and strive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the R universe, including the tidyverse, is growing rapidly indeed. I learned lots of new tricks from seasoned expeRts (like the unpacking operator &lt;code&gt;%&amp;lt;-%&lt;/code&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rdrr.io/cran/zeallot/man/operator.html&#34;&gt;zeallot package&lt;/a&gt;) and discovered so many cool packages I hadn’t been aware of. To name only three, in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HenrikBengtsson/future&#34;&gt;future&lt;/a&gt;: the promising heir to the popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/foreach/index.html&#34;&gt;foreach package&lt;/a&gt; in the parallel processing domain; developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HenrikBengtsson&#34;&gt;Henrik Bengtsson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EvaMaeRey/flipbookr&#34;&gt;flipbookr&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EvaMaeRey&#34;&gt;Gina Reynolds’&lt;/a&gt; side-by-side and step-by-step tool to illustrate how code turns into output. Great resource for teaching and demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidymodels/tune&#34;&gt;tune&lt;/a&gt;: the newest &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidymodels&#34;&gt;tidymodels&lt;/a&gt; family member; responsible for tuning hyperparameters. Presented by mastermind &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topepo&#34;&gt;Max Kuhn&lt;/a&gt;, it was great to see how the individual tidymodels components come together to soon form a powerful and consistent machine learning workflow. Exciting times ahead!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course the most important consequence of the healthy expansion of the R ecosystem is the existence of many new hex stickers ;-) . This was my first opportunity to become a hunter and gatherer of those colourful collectibles, and I managed to ultimately design a whole new look for my laptop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/pics/rstudioconf20_2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I’m gonna need a bigger laptop&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m gonna need a bigger laptop&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For all your R and Data Science needs check out the R for Data Science (R4DS) online learning community on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/R4DScommunity&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; and slack!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You’re probably not surprised to hear that there is an R package that lets you design your own hex stickers. It is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GuangchuangYu/hexSticker&#34;&gt;hexSticker&lt;/a&gt;. That name is probably even less surprising.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested to meet fellow R enthusiasts you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://jumpingrivers.github.io/meetingsR/&#34;&gt;find here&lt;/a&gt; a pretty comprehensive list of events and user groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
