<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data flow visuals - alluvial vs ggalluvial in R</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/06/06/visuals-alluvial-ggalluvial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/06/06/visuals-alluvial-ggalluvial/</guid>
      <description>I have long been a fan of creative data visualisation techniques. For me, the choice of visual representation is driven by both the type of data and the kind of question one wants to examine.
The power of its visualisation tools has been a major strength of the R language well before the ggplot2 package and the tidyverse burst onto the scene. Today’s post will be an introductory examination of two similar packages that allow us to study the connection and flow of data between different categorical features via alluvial plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidy evaluation in R - Simple Examples</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/24/tidy-eval-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/24/tidy-eval-examples/</guid>
      <description>The tidyverse philosophy introduced by Hadley Wickham has been a game changer for the R community. It is based on intuitive rules of what a tidy data set should look like: each variable is a column, each observation is a row (Wickham 2014). At its core, the tidyverse collection of R packages is powered by a consistent grammar of data manipulation and visualisation.
The tidyverse grammar makes it easier to manipulate data sets using simple expressions that reduce the syntactic overhead and allow you to focus on the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes a community great?</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/19/great-community-kaggledays19/</guid>
      <description>The easy answer to this question is: the people. Great people build great communities. Case not quite closed yet, though, because there is more to it. Even the most promising group of individuals needs certain conditions in order to grow into a strong and thriving community. The kind of community that lifts up its members beyond their individual capabilities and becomes more than the sum of their proverbial skills and contributions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prologue</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/08/prologue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/04/08/prologue/</guid>
      <description>This one is all about change. In many ways life is about change. Not all change is good, but without it there would be no evolution. No progress. And as much as we sometimes want certain moments to last, stagnation is rarely a good thing. Without attempting something new it is impossible to say whether it will succeed. I guess that’s a verbose way of saying: I decided to start a blog.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>