<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tidytuesday on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</title>
    <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/tags/tidytuesday/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tidytuesday on head spin - the Heads or Tails blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/tags/tidytuesday/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>TidyTuesday and Barplots with Images</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/04/28/gems-tidytuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2022/04/28/gems-tidytuesday/</guid>
      <description>This week, the Kaggle Hidden Gems Competition is featured in a special crossover event with the fantastic TidyTuesday project to further strengthen the connections between the R &amp;amp; Kaggle communities. The TidyTuesday participants are invited to expand their beautifully crafted data visuals into narrative notebooks on the Kaggle platform, and receive feedback and prizes for their work. This post will briefly describe my goals and motivation for this collaboration, and then show the code for one of my own visuals where I learned how to include images in ggplot2 barplots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidyverse evolutions: curly-curly operator and pivoting (feat. tidytuesday data &amp; leaflet visuals)</title>
      <link>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/11/07/tidy-curly-pivot-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heads0rtai1s.github.io/2019/11/07/tidy-curly-pivot-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>The tidyverse ecosystem is steadily growing and adapting to the needs of its users. As part of this evolution, existing tools are being replaced by new and better methods. As useful as this flexibility is to the strength of the system, sometimes it can be hard to keep track of all the changes. This blogpost will deal with two new developments: the ‘curly-curly’ operator for tidy evaluation and the new ‘pivot’ functions for data reshaping.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
